Register to The Seymour Shifrin Papers
Yale University Music Library
- Programs, 1950-1981; Series III; .4' (1 box)
  - Concerts Including Shifrin Works, III.A
    - Orchestral and Chamber Music
      - Quartets, strings, no. 3, 1967-1970; 5 items. (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 4, 1967-1969; 9 items. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 5, 1972-1978; 10 items. (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Serenade for five instruments, 1956-1973; 14 items. (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Sonata, violoncello, piano, 1956; 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Trios, piano, strings, 1975-1978; 7 items. (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Keyboard Works
      - Composition for piano, 1955; 6 items. (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Fantasy for piano, 1961; 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - The Modern temper, 1960-1969; 21 items. (Box 15, Folder 12)
        Includes letters.
      - Responses, 1976-1977; 4 items. (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Trauermusik, 1957-1969; 8 items. (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Choral Work
      - Chronicles, 1976; 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - Lament for Oedipus, 1956-1976; 5 items. (Box 15, Folder 14)
        From: Cantata to Sophoclean choruses.
      - The Odes of Shang, 1964-1979; 16 items. (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - More than one work
      - 1958-1979, 14 items. (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Concerts by Friends, III.B
    - 1956-1979, 23 items. (Box 15, Folder 17)
- Clippings, 1952-1982; Series IV; .2' (1 box)
  This series contains newspaper and magazine clippings concerning Shifrin and his friends. All have been photocopied onto acid-free paper and the originals were not kept. There are five subseries. Subseries A (Shifrin's Works and Performances) is arranged alphabetically within the same subdivisions used in Series IV: PROGRAMS. Subseries B-E are arranged in chronological order.
  - Shifrin's Works and Performances, IV.A
    - Songs (and other vocal)
      - Three songs, 1952; 3 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Satires of circumstance, 1965-1976; 9 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Orchestral and Chamber Music
      - Chamber symphony, 1963; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Concert piece for solo violin, 1962; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Duets, violin, piano, no date; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - In eius memoriam, 1974; 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - The Nick of time, 1978; 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Pieces, orchestra, 1960-1974; 11 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
        Includes typescript transcription of three reviews.
      - Quartets, strings (1949), 1953; 7 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 1, 1950-1962; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 2, 1962; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 3, 1967; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 4, 1967-1976; 13 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 5, 1974; 4 items. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Serenade for five instruments, 19T4; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Trios, piano, strings, 1975; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Keyboard Works
      - Fantasy for piano, 1961; 3 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - The Modern temper, 1960-1979; 13 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Trauermusik, 1957; 5 items. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Choral Works
      - Chronicles, 1976; 4 items. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Lament for Oedipus, 1961; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - The Odes of Shang, 1963-1977; 4 items. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - More than one work
      - 1969-1979, 4 items. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Articles by Shifrin, IV.B
    - no date, 2 items. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Biographical, IV.C
    - 1953-1979, 11 items. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Memorial Tributes, IV.D
    - 1979-1982, 3 items. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Concerts by Friends, IV.E
    - no date, 3 items. (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Writings, 1940-1979; Series V; 1.7' (5 boxes)
  The writings of Shifrin contain holograph and typescript reports and essays, student notebooks and exercises, and program notes on his music. The series is divided into five subseries. The first three (A-C) are arranged chronologically and the last two (D-E) are arranged alphabetically by title. Subseries A (Student Years) contains material written before 1944. Subseries B (Columbia Years) contains material written from 1944-1948.
  - Student Years, V.A
    - Notebooks, 13 items; Thirteen spiral-bound notebooks; 18-27 cm. (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
      Holographs in pencil and ink.
      Contain exercises, lecture notes, etc.
    - File cards, 2 items; Two set of file cards; 8 x 13 cm. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      Contain notes on music theory and Mozart's Don Giovanni.
    - Notes and Reports, 14 items; Loose sheets; 14-28 cm. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Holographs in pencil and ink and typescripts.
      Notes and reports on counterpoint, theory texts, and compositional techniques.
    - Lectures, etc., 1 item; One folder; 34 cm. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Sheets removed from a loose-leaf notebook.
      Contains lecture notes and exercises in counterpoint as well as music for string quartet and for piano.
  - Columbia Years, V.B
    - Lectures and Reports, 1 item; One folder; 28 cm. (Box 18, Folder 1)
      Holographs in pencil and typescripts.
      Contains lecture notes and reports from philosophy classes.
    - Reports, 1 item; One folder; 28 cm. (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Typescript reports for classes in literature and art.
    - Reports, 1 item; One folder; 28 cm. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Typescript reports for a class in 20th century trends in music.
    - Columbia University transcripts (1944-1948), 1 item; One folder; 28 cm. (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Typescripts, 1 item; One folder; 28 cm. (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Notes, 1 item; One folder; 28 cm. (Box 18, Folder 6)
      Contains lecture notes and harmony exercises from 1944-195.
  - Teaching Materials, V.C
    - Exercises, etc., 1 item; One folder; 28 x 34 cm. (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Holographs in pencil and ink and typescript photocopies.
      Contains exercises, analyses, musical examples, lesson plans, etc.
    - Notebooks, 6 items; Six spiral-bound notebooks; 27-30 cm. (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
      Contain teaching notes, analyses, musical examples, etc.
    - Notebooks, 6 items; Six spiral-bound notebooks; 15 cm. (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Holographs in ink and pencil in Seymour Shifrin's and Miriam Shifrin's hand.
      Contain letters, theory notes, diet record, etc.
  - Papers, Addresses, Essays, Etc., V.D
    - A Birthday Greeting, 1 item; [2] sheets of music; 23 cm. (Box 20, Folder 1)
      See also: I. MUSIC. B. Songs.
    - [Chopin], 1 item; 4 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Typescript (carbon).
      Essay for Atlantic Brief Lives, 1967.
    - [Composers as Teachers], 2 items; 8 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Typescript (photocopies).
      Transcription of interview for publication at Brandeis.
    - [Concerning contemporary music], 1 item; 3 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 20, Folder 4)
      Typescript.
    - Counterpoint, 1 item; [33] sheets; 28 cm. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      Typescript with corrections in pencil.
    - Counterpoint, 1 item; [51] p.; 20 cm.
      Spiral-bound note pad with draft for above.
      Contains additional unrelated jottings in pencil.
    - A Note from the Underground (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - A Note from the Underground, 3 items; 3 sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript with pencil and ink corrections and two carbon copies.
        In: Perspectives of new music (1962), Fall (I,i).
      - A Note from the Underground, 1 item; [6] p.; 22 cm.
    - [Structural Musical Development], 1 item; 3 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Typescript of a lecture.
    - Tomorrow's Theory Study (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Tomorrow's Theory Study, 6 items; 5 sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript and carbon copies with corrections in pencil and ink.
        Panel discussion for College Music Symposium, 1961.
      - Tomorrow's Theory Study, 1 item; [3] sheets; 28 cm.
    - [The University as the last open city] (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - [The University as the last open city], 1 item; [42] p.; 25 cm.
        Reprint. Originally published in: College Music Symposium (1970), p. 92.
      - [The University as the last open city], 4 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        Typescript and three photocopies.
    - [Valued qualities in music], 2 items; [1] sheet; 22 x 28 cm. (Box 20, Folder 10)
      Holograph signed, on a page from a C.F. Peters catalogue (photocopies).
    - [Review of Salzer's book on Schenker], 1 item; [7] p.; 28 cm. (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - [Review of Style and Idea] (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - Style and Idea: Selected Writings of Arnold Schoenberg. Edited by Leonard Stein. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1975., 2 items; [9] p.; 23 cm.
        Reprint. Originally published in: Perspectives of new music (1975), p. 174-181.
      - [Review of Style and Idea], 2 items; [14] sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript and carbon copy with corrections in ink.
      - [Review of Style and Idea], 1 item; [20] p.; 28-33 cm.
    - Miscellaneous jottings, 1 item; [4] folded sheets; 28 cm. (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Program Notes, V.E
    - Chamber symphony, 4 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm. (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Typescript and photocopies.
    - Chronicles, 6 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm. (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Typescript and photocopies with additions in ink.
    - Duets, violin, piano, 4 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm. (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - In eius memoriam, 3 items; [4] sheets; 28 cm. (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - The Modern temper, 4 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm. (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - The Nick of time (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - The Nick of time, 2 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        Typescript and photocopy.
      - The Nick of time, 1 item; [1] sheet 28 cm.
        Photocopy of a progrcm.
    - The Odes of Shang (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - The Odes of Shang, 3 items; [3] sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript photocopies.
      - The Odes of Shang, 1 item; [2] sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript with corrections in ink.
      - The Odes of Shang, 1 item; [3] p.; 19 cm.
      - The Odes of Shang, 1 item; [13] sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript (carbon) and photocopies.
        Texts and program notes from concerts including The Odes of Shang.
    - Pieces, orchestra, 1 item; [2] sheets; 28 cm. (Box 21, Folder 12)
      Typescript photocopy of a progrcm.
    - A Renaissance garland (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - A Renaissance garland, 1 item; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        Also contains notes for Waltz (1977).
      - A Renaissance garland, 2 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        Holograph in ink and typescript.
        Also contains notes for Waltz and string quartet no. 5.
    - Responses, 6 items; (1] sheet; 28 cm. (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Satires of circumstance (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - Satires of circumstance, 8 items; [4] sheets; 28 cm.
        Intended for use as record jacket notes.
      - Satires of circumstance, 1 item; [2] sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript with corrections in ink and pencil.
        Draft for above.
      - Satires of circumstance, 1 item; [2] sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript photocopies of text.
      - Satires of circumstance, 1 item; [1] sheet; 19 cm.
        Notes in response to a letter to Seymour Shifrin.
    - Serenade for five instruments, 1 item; [1] sheet; 28 cm. (Box 21, Folder 11)
      Photocopy of a program with notes in unknown hand.
    - Quartets, strings, no. 3 (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 3, 1 item; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        Typescript photocopy of a program.
      - Quartets, strings, no. 3, 1 item; [2] sheets; 28 cm.
        Typescript with ink and pencil corrections.
    - Quartets, strings, no. 4 (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 4, 1 item; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
      - Quartets, strings, no. 4, 1 item; [2] sheets; 28 cm.
    - Quartets, strings, no. 5 (Box 23, Folder 13)
      - Quartets, strings, no. 5, 1 item; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        Typescript photocopy.
      - Quartets, strings, no. 5, 1 item; [1] sheet; 34 cm.
        With miscellaneous jottings.
    - Trios, piano, strings (Box 21, Folder 14)
      - Trios, piano, strings, 3 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
        Typescript and photocopy of a program.
      - Trios, piano, strings, 2 items; [1] sheet; 28 cm.
- Biographical Material, 1955-1975; Series VI; .2' (1 box)
  This series contains resumes and bio-bibliographical materials arranged in chronological order. Most are typescript photocopies, some with notes in Shifrin's hand.
  - Bio-bibliographies, 1955-1975; 21 items. (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Manuscripts given to Shifrin by Roger Sessions, 1937-1953; Series VII; .2' (1 box)
  This series contains two pieces of music given to Shifrin while Shifrin was teaching at the University of California at Berkeley. Included are Sessions' Sonata for unaccompanied violin and the Sonata for piano, which is incomplete.
  - [Sonata, violin] Sonata for violin (unaccompanied) / Roger Sessions, 1953 Mar.-May; 1 score ([47] p.); 32-38 cm. (Box 23, Folder 1)
    Photocopy of holograph, with additions in ink.
    Title page bears inscription from Sessions to Seymour Shifrin.
    On title page: To Robert Gross.
    First movement separate from movements 2-4.
    Two additional photocopies of 4th movement laid in.
  - [From my diary] Pages from a diary / Roger Sessions, [8] sheets of music; 33 cm. (Box 23, Folder 2)
    Dates at end of each movement: I. (Princeton, 1937 May-1939 Nov.) -- II. (Colorado Springs, 1939 Aug.-Princeton, 1940 Mar.) -- III. (Colorado Springs, 1939 Aug.)
    Incomplete. Lacks pp. 4-7 and pp. 13 to end.
    Formerly listed in this register as a piano sonata, this piece was identified in 2006 by the Sessions scholar Andrea Olmstead as "Pages from a diary," later published under the title "From my diary."
- Miscellaneous Items, 1940-1972; Series VIII; .4' (1 box)
  This series contains three subseries. Subseries A (Photographs) contains photographs of Shifrin and his immediate family. Subseries B (Memorabilia) is arranged alphabetically by title or supplied title and contains address books, diplomas, passports, and other memorabilia. Subseries C (Notes by Susan Blaustein) contains notes written while Susan Blaustein prepared the initial organization of the papers.
  - Photographs, VIII.A
    - Photographs of Shifrin and his family., 39 items. (Box 24, Folder 1)
      In part, negative.
  - Memorabilia, VIII.B
    - Address books and loose addresses, 3 items. (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Diplomas and certificates, 1940-1959; 8 items. (Box 24, Folder 3-5)
    - Passports for Seymour Shifrin and his wife, 1951-1972; 12 items. (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Post cards, maps, etc., 16 items. (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Notes by Susan Blaustein, VIII.C
    - Notes by Susan Blaustein (Box 24, Folder 8)
- Musical Instruments, no date; Series IX; 10.9' (11 boxes)
  This series contains a description of percussion instruments owned by Shifrin, some of which were made by him for use in his compositions. The instruments are arranged alphabetically by type (classification) of percussion instrument. Those instruments intended for use in a specific composition by Shifrin have been so identified.
  - Bells (clapper)
    - Brass, cowbells, 5 items; 6-11 cm. (Box 25)
      Origin: India.
      Iin graduated sizes, on leather string.
    - Brass, cowbell, 1 item; 8 cm. (Box 25)
      On rope handle.
    - Brass, cylindrical, 3 items; 7-8 cm. (Box 25)
      In graduated sizes, on string.
    - Brasso cylindrical, 3 items; 10 cm. (Box 25)
    - Metal, 3 items; 5 cm. (Box 25)
  - Bells (pellet)
    - Pellet (sleigh) bells, 2 items. (Box 25)
      Mounted on wood handle.
  - Bells (struck)
    - Brass, cowbell, 1 item; 12 cm. (Box 25)
    - Brass, cowbells, 4 items; 29 x 35 x 23 cm. (Box 26)
      Mounted on wood stand.
      For: The Odes of Shang.
    - Brass, cylindrical, 7 items; 11 cm. (Box 25)
  - Blocks
    - Wood, hollow, 5 items; 30 x 10 x 10 cm. (Box 27)
      With pitched grooves.
  - Chimes
    - Wind chime, bamboo, 1 item; 54 x 48 cm. (Box 28)
    - Wind chime, glass, 1 item; 13 cm. diameter. (Box 29)
      Origin: Japan.
  - Claves
    - Claves, 2 items; 25 cm. (Box 29)
      One set, mounted on wood handle.
  - Cymbals
    - Cymbals, 2 items. (Box 29)
      One set finger (hand).
  - Drums
    - Dholak, 1 item; 39 x 18 cm. (Box 30)
      For: The Nick of time.
    - Dholki, 1 item; 21 x 15 cm. (Box 31)
    - Kelontong, 2 items; 10 cm. diameter. (Box 31)
      Origin: Java
    - Mridanga, 1 item; 40 x 14 cm. diameter (top) x l7 cm. diameter (bottom). (Box 32)
      For: The Nick of time
    - Tabla, 1 item; 26 x 25 cm. diameter (top) x 7 cm. diameter (bottom). (Box 33)
    - Udekkiya, 1 item; 23 x 15 cm. (Box 31)
    - Cylindrical double-headed drum, 1 item; 18 x 3O cm. (Box 34)
      Origin: Korea
    - Frame drum, with handle, 1 item; 20 cm. diameter. (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Hard felt stick, 1 item; 34 cm. (Box 29)
      For striking cowbells mounted on wood stand.
    - Ban pod, 1 item; 60 cm. (Box 30)